בוקר
טוב. Boker tov. Welcome to the penultimate דף daf of ביצה. Beitzah.
Okay, and we pick up from, looks like here, ל"ט מלאכות lamed-tes
melachos here, which don't all apply equally on יום טוב. Yom Tov.
On דף ל"ט. daf lamed-tes. No, I'm just saying, as we wrap
up, there are 39 דפים, dapim, it goes up to דף מ',
daf mem, but it starts on דף ב'. daf beiz. So okay,
you can figure out the significance of that. So we pick up
with the משנה, Mishnah, I left you an easy דף daf yesterday
to do, so anyway.
So where we pick up now, so we're dealing again with these
issues about תחומים tchumim and, you know, which is a שבת Shabbos
הלכה, halacha, but again because there's all this issue about food and
because I, maybe because carrying
is less restrictive on יום טוב, Yom Tov, you don't need, you
know, you don't need an עירוב eiruv and you don't need walls
and so on, so maybe the concern about transporting food is much
greater, which is true. When you think about תחומים tchumim on שבת,
Shabbos, you're thinking about how far you go, right? Does anybody ever
say you can't take, you know, your objects or your food 2000
אמות amos outside the city on שבת? Shabbos? Of course you can't,
it's carrying. Okay, so I think that although תחומים tchumim is obviously
equally applies on שבת Shabbos and יום טוב, Yom Tov, the issues
about how far you can take your objects and particularly your food
is specifically a יום טוב Yom Tov concern. So we continue with
that. Let's take a look.
הגחלת, Hagacheles, a coal, an ember, כרגלי הבעלים, k'raglei haba'alim, goes like
the owners', like everything else, goes by the owners' תחום. tchum.
ושלהבת, V'shalheves, but the flame, בכל מקום, b'chol makom, has no restrictions,
it's not considered to be a actual thing. Now how do you
take a flame without taking the coal? Well, you light your match
to it. So you have a burning fire and I say, 'cause
I forgot to light my יארצייט yahrtzeit candle on ערב erev on
יום טוב Yom Tov whatever and I need now to light my
stovetop and I go and I take your flame and I use
it to light my stovetop, am I limited by your תחום? tchum?
And the answer is no. If I were to take your actual
candle I couldn't bring it outside of your תחום, tchum, but if
I take the flame, the flame is not considered to be a
real thing and therefore it's not limited.
So that's why is the flame is not considered to be, is
considered to be a new flame?
Or you could say it's considered new, but as we'll continue, we'll
see why it's not just limited to the idea that it's being
transferred anew. But yes, in that scenario you could say it's not
the same one. But let's keep on going, we'll see why I
said what I did. Okay, גחלת של הקדש, Gacheles shel hekdesh, if
you have a coal owned by the בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash, מועלין
בו, mo'alin bo, there's מעילה me'ilah like anything else owned by the
בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash. ושלהבת, V'shalheves, but if you have the flame
of the בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash, לא נהנין ולא מועלין. lo nehenin
v'lo mo'alin. You are rabbinically allowed to derive הנאה, hana'ah, but you
do not biblically transgress the prohibition of מעילה. me'ilah. Now, again, this
could be the scenario that you transferred the flame and you're benefiting
from the transfer of the flame, or it could just be the
benefit that I don't know, you're, you know, you're going in and
you're, you're getting light from a flame that's burning off of a
בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash off of the coal. Now which raises an
interesting question because I accept the idea that you'll consider the flame
to have אין בו ממש ein bo mamash and it's not really
owned and it's not really a thing, but isn't getting benefit from
the flame getting benefit from the coal indirectly? You know and then
that gets or maybe even directly and that gets to whole discussions
in the גמרא Gemara about you know where the גמרא Gemara talks
about that when you burn wood, are you deriving benefit from the
wood as it's burning or are you only getting the benefit after
it's been destroyed, you know, because you're getting it from what's already
been burned? It is a little bit confusing here because it seems
like now we're not just talking about when it's been transferred. It
seems like you're actually directly are getting from a flame that's coming
off of a coal or some obviously type of a fuel and
nevertheless because your it's the flame that you're getting benefit from, it's
not considered to be a you know at least a biblical מעילה
me'ilah and somehow that does not make it considered like benefit from
the from the fuel, from the from the coal, yes.
Yeah, in our terms it's kind of like trying to understand the
relationship between matter and energy.
Oh that's right, which in a way is what fire is, but
yes.
Right, it's the the conversion of mass to energy.
Right, it's a good point. Yeah, it's a good point. Yeah, it's
a good point. I mean, I wonder what happens if you take
your let's say like, let's say you were to take your you
know match and touch it against or whatever your straw and touch
it against an ember of הקדש hekdesh and then it got on
flame. I assume that would be מעילה, me'ilah, you directly got benefit
from the ember of הקדש, hekdesh, right?
But it depends on what we said before, whether after it's already
been converted from mass to energy, it's no longer related to the...
Right, but if it's right, so that's the question, but if you've
got like this smoldering hot thing, this isn't a flame, it's just
like really, really hot ember, and you touch a piece of straw
to it, presumably that's a case of getting מעילה, me'ilah, of getting
some benefit from it. But if you got the flame coming from
the top of it and you touch your straw to the flame,
or you, you know, do this or however you benefit from the
flame in some way, then it's not. So again, it's a little
hard to fully get your head around it. המוציא גחלת לרשות הרבים
חייב, Hamotzi gacheles l'reshus harabbim chayav, if you take a coal to
a public domain you're liable. Taking an ember out to a רשות
הרבים, reshut harabbim, you're חייב, chayav, because it's an object and that's
considered to be a significant enough to be a שיעור shiur and
whatever. You'd be carrying on שבת. shabbat. Now we're talking obviously about
שבת. shabbat. ושלהבת פטור, veshalevet patur, but if you take out the
flame, you are exempt, because again now that's not a real thing.
Now how do you take out a flame without taking out the
thing that's holding onto it? We will see in the גמרא. gemara.
I have an interesting idea about that which the גמרא gemara didn't
say, but okay. Let's first see what the גמרא gemara says.
תנו רבנן. tanna rabbanan. חמישה דברים נאמרו בגחלת, chamisha devarim ne'emru begachelet,
five things were said regarding the coal.
כגחלת כרגלי הבעלים, kagachelet keraglei habe'alim, for תחומין techumin purposes, it goes
by the owner's like anything else the owner owns. ובשלהבת בכל מקום,
beshalevet bechol makom, but the flame can be taken anywhere. It's not
a real thing.
So therefore, by the way, that's also the reason why it's not
just an issue of the new thing is yours, because if the
new thing was yours, it wouldn't say בכל מקום, bechol makom, it
would say the person who transfers the flame. בכל
מקום bechol makom means there's absolutely no limit, right? So therefore because
it's not really a thing.
גחלת של הקדש מועלין בה, gachelet shel hekdesh mo'alin bah, so the
coal of הקדש hekdesh you would transgress the prohibition of מעילה. me'ilah.
ובשלהבת לא נהנין ולא מועלין, beshalevet lo nehenin velo mo'alin, the שלהבת
shalevet is rabbinically forbidden but there's no מעילה. me'ilah. גחלת של עבודה
זרה אסורה, gachelet shel avodah zarah asurah,
a coal related to עבודה זרה, avodah zarah, maybe it was on
an altar for an idol, so it's forbidden.
ושלהבת מותרת, veshalevet muteret, and the flame is permissible. I know, it's
wild, not even an איסור דרבנן, issur derabbanan, which the גמרא gemara
is going to ask about. By the way, it's not מעילה me'ilah
obviously. מעילה me'ilah is only a phrase by הקדש. hekdesh. It's אסורה,
asurah, I mean it's a biblical prohibition, but it's not the category
obviously of מעילה. me'ilah. המוציא גחלת לרשות הרבים חייב. hamotzi gachelet lirshut
harabbim chayav. If you take out the coal, then you're חייב. chayav.
ושלהבת פטור, veshalevet patur, if you take out the flame, you're exempt.
המודר הנאה מחבירו, hamudar hana'ah mechaveiro, if basically I'm in a position
where I have forsworn by a נדר neder getting benefit from you,
I say that I take a vow that all of your things
are אסור asur to me. So אסור בגחלתו, asur begacheltov, I cannot
use your embers. ומותר בשלהבתו. umutar beshalevto. And but I could however
go over and transfer a flame from you. That's not your thing.
Okay? Basically it raised the whole question like, is there a concept
of ownership of flame? Do I have to ask you for permission
if you have a burning fire? Let's say it would not be
an issue of trespass, right? If you have a burning fire, would
I have to ask you for permission? You went ahead, you made
here a little bit of bonfire in this public space, I'm sitting
next to you, okay? Can I just stick
my stick on it or my straw on it and transfer some
of that flame? Do you own the fire? Right? I think to
some degree that's what we're talking about. I mean it seems like
you don't necessarily own it or else that's why there's no limit
of the
תחומין techumin and so on.
So that's the המודר הנאה mudar hana'ah as well. Again, you could
make sure you own it, but it's not considered real benefit, but
it seems like it's saying the flame isn't a thing to be
owned. As Dov said, it's energy, it's not a thing.
Okay, now yes.
So this is a תוספתא? tosefta? Mhm. The תוספתא tosefta was compiled
in ארץ ישראל. eretz yisrael. Yeah. Although it has the Persian religion
made a lot of use of fire and I was wondering if
they, oh, that's interesting. Yeah. Or maybe they didn't consider it to
be idolatry, I don't know.
No, no, they definitely did consider it to be idolatry. But here
we're talking about the technical prohibition of איסורי הנאה, issurei hana'ah, which
goes to the object. By the way, look at the side, the
side adds another line which is מברכין על השלהבת ואין מברכין על
הגחלת. mevarchin al hashalevet ve'ein mevarchin al hagachelet. Right? So you make
בורא מאורי האש borei meorei ha'esh only with on the flame, but
not on the coal. So actually in terms of a ברכה, bracha,
you need a flame, right? But in terms of defining it as
an object and a thing and something to be owned, you do
not. I mean look, you don't need
thingness of something to make a ברכה. bracha. You make a ברכה
bracha on thunder, right? So you don't need it to be like
a physical thing, but to be owned and to be a thing,
it does not apply by the flame.
There was an atomistic theory in antiquity.
I don't know to what degree the atomistic theory applied to things
that cannot be touched. I mean, I guess fire could be touched,
but not in the same way. Did the atomistic theory apply to
things that weren't perceived as matter?
I just don't know the answer to that. Yeah. This is much
more scientifically advanced than one would have expected. Well,
we're חז"ל. chazal. Yeah, basically came much closer to the scientific understanding
of today than one would have expected.
But again, I don't think they framed it scientifically. It's just like
physically it's not something that can be, I mean, I guess it's
why would you say wow, why is it different than I don't
know water, you know? I mean it's okay, you touch it, it's
hot. Somehow you can't transfer... Yeah. Okay, interesting phenomenon.
All right, so now the
גמרא gemara says like this. מאי שנא שלהבת עבודה זרה דשריא ומאי
שנא דהקדש דאסירא. mai shna shalevet avodah zarah desharya mai shna dehekdesh
de'asura.
Why is a flame of עבודה זרה avodah zarah מותר לכתחילה mutar
lechatchila and a flame of הקדש hekdesh at least אסור דרבנן? assur
derabbanan? So the גמרא gemara says עבודה זרה דמאיסה בדילי אינשי מינה
avodah zarah demi'isa badilei inishe minah because עבודה זרה... avodah zarah... avodah
zarah is sort of disgusting and therefore people separate from it, meaning
fundamentally there's a taboo around עבודה זרה. avodah zarah. So לא גזרו
בה רבנן, lo gazru bah rabbanan, the Rabbis did not have to
make a גזירה, gezeirah, they knew you would avoid it anyway.
הקדש דלא מאיס ולא בדילי אינשי מיניה hekdesh delo ma'is velo badilei
inshi mineih and הקדש hekdesh which is not disgusting and people don't
separate themselves from it, of course it's more they separate themselves from
it than from חולין, chullin, but relative to עבודה זרה avodah zarah
they don't separate themselves from it. They go into the בית המקדש,
Beit HaMikdash, they deal with הקדש hekdesh on a regular basis. So
גזרו בה רבנן, gazru bah rabbanan, they needed to make a safeguard.
But again, I still don't know the exact answer. The גמרא Gemara
does not exactly describe the scenario. We'll get to a scenario in
a minute about carrying, but I don't exactly know when it says
you can derive benefit, does it mean like only in a case
of a transferred flame? But even if you're transferring the flame, you
stick your piece of your stick on a fire of עבודה זרה
avodah zarah and you transfer it, but okay, that's still ultimately rooted
in the coal. And certainly if you directly get let's say some
light benefit from the thing that's growing off of the coal. But
maybe אי נמי, ee nami, like that stage as we said, maybe
the coal is already considered to be nonexistent. The גמרא Gemara here
by the שבת Shabbat case does get to the issue of how
do you have a flame without a coal? So let's take a
look. המוציא
גחלת
לרשות
הרבים
חייב שלהבת
פטור.
hamotzi
gachelet
lerishut harabbim chayav shalhevet patur. If you take out the גחלת, gachelet,
the ember, the coal, you're חייב chayav on שבת, Shabbat, but on,
excuse me, but
the flame you're exempt. The גמרא Gemara says והתניא המוציא שלהבת כל
שהוא חייב. vehatanya hamotzi shalhevet kol shehu chayav. But one minute, we
have a ברייתא baraita that says even a tiny flame you're חייב.
chayav. So it's the opposite of this. So אמר רב ששת כגון
שהוציאה בקיסם. amar Rav Sheshet kegon shehotzi'ah bekisam.
No, the case where you're חייב chayav is when it's not just
the flame, when it's being taken out on a little twig, on
a little toothpick. Of course, so that means the case that you're
פטור patur is just the flame. How do you take out just
the flame? So we'll get to that in a minute. But first,
the case that you're חייב chayav is when you took it out
on a little toothpick. So the גמרא Gemara says ותיפוק לי משום
קיסם. veteipok lei mishum kisam. If you're taking it on a toothpick,
who needs to talk about the fire? You took out the toothpick.
So the גמרא Gemara says no, דלית ביה שיעורא. deleit beih shiura.
No, the toothpick isn't big enough to be חייב chayav for itself.
דתנן המוציא עצים, detnan hamotzi etzim, if you take out wood, כדי
לבשל ביצה קלה. kedei levashel beitah kalah.
You need enough wood in order to cook a light egg, which
means like a chicken's egg, an egg that cooks easily. Okay, so
you took out a match. A match is not enough wood to
be חייב chayav for, you took out a burning match. But because
the flame is now rooted in a physical object, that gives significance
to the flame and now you're חייב chayav for the flame. Right,
so now it sounds like at least for שבת Shabbat הלכות, halachot,
when the flame is rooted in a physical object, it is considered
a thing, an object that has significance. Which then makes us wonder
about all the earlier cases. Maybe all the earlier cases also, if
it's rooted in a physical object it's considered a thing. The גמרא
Gemara never goes back to explore that. Let's take a look at
another case. אביי אמר כגון דשייפי מנא משחא ואתלי ביה נורא. Abaye
amar kegon deshaifi mana mishcha ve'atlei beih nura. No,
not with a match. What you did is even when it wasn't
like the thing that was burning wasn't obviously being burned. Let's say
you smeared a vessel with oil and you lit it on fire.
So you have a מנא, mana, a thing, a vessel. Could be
a piece of cloth? I don't think a cloth. I think he's
trying to take a case where you don't see something being consumed.
Obviously what's being consumed is the oil. But you have a patina
of oil on a vessel and you lit it. And now the
oil is burning. Okay, but there's no obvious like wick and there's
no obvious like thing being consumed. Obviously what's being consumed is the
oil. Okay. And the גמרא Gemara is going to actually assume in
a minute that it's actually a piece of pottery. So the גמרא
Gemara says ותיפוק לי משום מנא. veteipok lei mishum mana. How about,
well okay, you're carrying the vessel. חספא, chaspa, a piece of pottery,
it's not a full vessel. ותיפוק לי משום חספא. veteipok lei mishum
chaspa. Okay, but you're carrying the piece of pottery. דלית ביה שיעורא.
deleit beih shiura. No, it's not big enough from the pottery perspective.
דתנן, detnan, we taught in a משנה, Mishnah, חרס, cheres, how much
pottery do you have to take out in order to be חייב,
chayav, you know, broken piece of pottery? כדי ליתן בין פצים לחברו,
kedei liten bein patzim lechavero, to put between beams in a house,
you know, you like fill them up with little pieces of wood
or whatever in order to stabilize them. דברי רבי יהודה. divrei Rabbi
Yehuda. So it's not enough pottery to be חייב, chayav, but because
you have the flame on it, that gives significance to the flame.
The flame is now rooted in a physical object, so you're חייב
chayav for taking out a flame. So now we see the flame
is different when it's rooted in a physical object, which of course
raises the question: So what's the scenario that you carry without it
being connected to a physical object? So the גמרא Gemara says okay,
אלא הא דתנן המוציא שלהבת פטור היכי משכחת לה? ela ha detnan
hamotzi shalhevet patur heichi mishkachat lah?
Where would you have an example that you would be exempt for
taking out a flame? כגון דאדיי אדויי לרשות הרבים. kegon de'adei aduyei
lerishut harabbim. You pushed it into the רשות הרבים. rishut harabbim. What
does that mean? So רש"י Rashi says you've got a fire and
then you blow it or you wave it and something over the
line between your רשות reshut and the רשות הרבים rishut harabbim catches
fire. But the thing is, something else only, meaning something else has
to start burning out there in the רשות הרבים. rishut harabbim. But
the point is, the thing that was anchored in your רשות reshut
never moved and the thing that's now burning was always there. So
you never had like the movement of the thing in the thing
that it was anchored on, you know. So somehow that's the scenario.
Now by the way... I thought in the case of how do
you have that you can carry it without being חייב chayav for
the thing you're carrying it on, as opposed to the לית ביה
שיעורא, leys bei shiura, I thought well let's say just like your
clothes are on fire.
It's a little bit too of a gruesome scenario, so you're not
חייב chayav for your clothes, but the fire, the fire is that
would be an example where you're not חייב, chayav, hopefully but probably
there you're in the process of saving your life or something. Anyway,
but it does now go back and raise the question, if for
שבת Shabbos purposes when it's rooted in a physical object it's considered
a thing, so maybe that's true in all these earlier cases as
well. So in all these other cases maybe the only case that
you're פטור pattur is when you've transferred it from the original object,
right? So again if I go to this flame of עבודה זרה
avodah zarah and heat myself by it or use it as a
reading light maybe I'd be חייב. chayav. It's rooted in a גחלת
gacheles of עבודה זרה. avodah zarah. I'm חייב. chayav. Only when I
take it away from its original rooting in the גחלת gacheles maybe
only then is it considered to be not a thing of real
עבודה זרה, avodah zarah, not a thing of ממש. mamash. Okay, left
unexplored by the גמרא. Gemara. Yes.
So if I carry a toothpick out on
שבת? Shabbat? Yeah. I've violated a biblical prohibition according to some, but
I'm not חייב chayav because it's less than a שיעור. shiur.
Well that gets to the question of when you do less than
a שיעור shiur have you violated but you're not liable to punishment
or have you not violated? So that's a מחלוקת, machlokes, yeah that's
an interesting conceptual question there. Okay, now next. So that's the flame
issue, quite fascinating. Next,
משנה. Mishnah. בור של יחיד כרגלי היחיד. Bor shel yachid keraglei hayachid.
If you have a private well then the water in the well
is yours and it goes by your
תחום. tchum. ושל אנשי אותו העיר כרגלי אנשי אותו העיר. Veshel anshei
oso ha'ir keraglei anshei oso ha'ir. If it's owned by the city
then it goes by the you know by the generic boundaries of
the city which means two thousand אמות amos outside of the city.
If a few people in the city have moved their תחום tchum
because you know they made an ערוב תחומין eiruv tchumin that doesn't
change it. This is the city's water and it goes by the
city as a collective and goes by the two thousand אמות amos
around the city and that's how the water of the city well
would go. ושל עולי בבל, Veshel olei bavel, and how about wells
that are made for people that come from בבל, Bavel, you know
that made עליה aliyah and came for the רגל? regel? So those
were made specifically for people outside the city, they were made for
travelers, right? So it's not owned by any collective, it's available for
travelers, for whoever needs it. So that's כרגלי הממלא. keraglei hamemallei. That
goes by the person who fills it up with water who fills
it up on יום טוב. Yom Tov. You come on יום טוב,
Yom Tov, it's the רגל. regel. By the way, you've got to
love the fact that here this משנה, Mishnah, right? Which is written
presumably at least a
hundred years after the חורבן הבית, Churban HaBayis, it still talks about
like עולי בבל olei Bavel as like a contemporary phenomenon. It didn't
say עוברי דרכים, ovrei drachim, right? So again like evoking that sense
that you know we're still being עולה לרגל. oleh laregel. Anyway, but
that does not owned by a collective, so it goes by the
person who filled it up. Now רש״י Rashi makes a point: Why
does it go by the person who filled it up? If it
starts יום טוב Yom Tov being ownerless, okay, what should its status
be? So yesterday there was an opinion we quoted of רבי יוחנן
בן נורי Rabbi Yochanan ben Nuri that says if it starts יום
טוב Yom Tov ownerless, it קונה שביתה koneh shvisah in its place.
So it's two thousand אמות amos from its location, not from the
person who filled it up, right? So that's one possibility. That's not
what's being said. The other possibility is it's like the גמרא Gemara
said before about גחלת. gacheles. It's בכל מקום. bechol makom. It has
no limit. It doesn't define its own תחום, tchum, it didn't start
יום טוב Yom Tov being part of another person's possession, so it's
not limited by any תחום. tchum. Okay, that would have been a
more reasonable thing. The idea of רגלי הממלא raglei hamemallei is again
this concept of ברירה. breirah. If I come and fill it up
on יום טוב, Yom Tov, then even though when it started יום
טוב Yom Tov it was ownerless, we say since on יום טוב
Yom Tov I wound up owning it, retroactively when יום טוב Yom
Tov began it was always considered to be under my control, because
in the future it would be under my control and therefore it
goes by my domain and not by its own domain and not
by no domain. That's the assumption of the משנה. Mishnah. Let's take
a look at the גמרא. Gemara. רמי ליה רבא לרב נחמן. Rami
leh Rava leRav Nachman. רבא Rava threw a contradiction to רב נחמן.
Rav Nachman. תנן, Tenan, אמר, amar, it says בור של יחיד כרגלי
היחיד, bor shel yachid keraglei hayachid, private well goes by the owner,
the private owner. ורמינהו U'reminhu on this, הנהרות המושכין והמעיינות הנובעין הרי
הן כרגלי כל אדם. Haneharos hamoshchin vehama'ayanos hanov'in harei hen keraglei kol
adam. So you know rivers that are running and wells that are
sort of flowing go by any person, meaning not so again they're
like the example we gave before that they did not start שבת
Shabbat with any particular ownership and therefore they're not limited by anybody,
not by the
owner there is no owner and not by the person who fills
it up, it has absolutely no תחום, tchum, no limit. So now
presumably he assumes that we're talking even if it's under private ownership.
Now if it's under private ownership why should that be? So the
reason is the key word here is מושכין moshchin and נובעין. nov'in.
It starts שבת Shabbat not in a fixed location. It's moving or
יום טוב. Yom Tov. And since it's moving, it's flowing and moving
and running, therefore it can't be קונה שביתה. koneh shvisah. To be
קונה שביתה koneh shvisah it has to be at rest. So it's
something that even though it has an owner is never קונה שביתה
koneh shvisah and therefore has no. So the obvious distinction is different.
This is a flowing; our משנה mishna says בור. bor. Yeah. So
the גמרא Gemara says, I don't even understand the question. So the
גמרא Gemara says אמר רבא Amar Rava or אמר רב Amar Rav
or whoever it is here,
הכא במאי עסקינן, hacha b'mai askinan, here what we talking about? במכונסים,
bi'mekhunasim, it's collected rain water, it's not flowing, which is a simple
case of בור. bor. איתמר נמי אמר חייא בר אבא אמר שמואל,
itmar nami Amar Chiya bar Abba Amar Shmuel, במכונסים. bi'mekhunasim. Okay. But
we introduced this idea that it could be owned privately, but if
it is flowing, it also is not קונה שביתה. koneh shevisah. So
עולי בבל Olei Bavel כרגלי הממלא. ki'raglei ha'memaleh. Now we get to
think about the עולי בבל Olei Bavel for the travelers that is
not considered like a city, a collective ownership. This is considered a
הפקר hefker or not owned or available to all but not a
sense of a sense of a collective; or if it is a
collective, it's a collective of כלל ישראל Klal Yisrael which doesn't have
a particular תחום. tchum. Okay. So therefore it goes by, but we'll
assume הפקר hefker and it goes by the person who fills it
up, again, not שכל אדם, she'kol adam, but again רש"י Rashi says
we're assuming ברירה. brirah. So once the person fills it up on
יום טוב Yom Tov and winds up owning it on יום טוב
Yom Tov retroactively it's like it was always his and therefore it
goes by his תחום. tchum. Yes.
So sorry to go back to במכונסים, bi'mekhunasim, the פשט pshat is
the במכונסים bi'mekhunasim are like flowing, are like?
No. Our case in the משנה mishna that a בור bor goes
by has a תחום tchum is collected rain water. The case of
the ברייתא Braita that it doesn't have a תחום tchum is when
it is flowing water.
Right, I get, I guess I'm bothered by how could anyone have
ever even asked the question if it said בור?
bor? Exactly. Exactly. Yeah, I don't know.
Could it be a well?
Yeah, I mean if it's a live water well. בור. bor.
A בור bor is never a well.
No, I don't know, you know, is it באר? be'er? I don't
know if it would be so precise.
A בור bor is always collected water. Well, if you were around
טבריה Tveria you would have had hot springs.
Yeah, I mean if the water coming in is coming from an
underground, from an underground source, right? No, no, you have a well
that is like our מקווה mikvah that collects rain water, right? Then
you have a well that you dig deep, deep like אברהם, Avraham,
right? You know, he dug deep and he found water. That's נובעים
novim because that's water that's coming through moving, but
that's what I'm saying.
Right, I
guess, I guess they thought that it wasn't, I guess they thought
it wasn't being precise. All right. Now, איתמר. itmar. So now so
okay so our משנה mishna says של עולי בבל כרגלי הממלא, shel
Olei Bavel ki'raglei ha'memaleh, which again assumes like an idea of הפקר.
hefker. מילא ונתן לחברו. mila venasan l'chavero. Let's say you filled it
up and you gave to your friend. רב נחמן אמר כרגלי מי
שנתמלאו לו. Rav Nachman amar ki'raglei mi she'nitmilu lo. It goes for
by the person for whom it was filled. I filled it up
and gave it to Charlie. רב ששת אמר כרגלי הממלא. Rav Sheshet
amar ki'raglei ha'memaleh. No, it goes by the filler, it goes by
me. Now, רש"י Rashi immediately jumps in and says we are not
talking about I filled it up for myself and then I gave
it to Charlie. That's the משנה. mishna. I filled it up for
myself, it's mine, and now I give it to Charlie so it
doesn't matter since I was the first one to take possession of
it, it goes by my תחום, tchum, not by Charlie's תחום, tchum,
end of story. But let's say it's not that. Let's say it's
a
רבקה Rivka and אליעזר Eliezer story. So Charlie comes and he says,
oh could I? I say, oh Charlie you look so thirsty let
me fill you up some water. And I go to the well
and I fill him up this water from this public well from
this עולי בבל Olei Bavel and I give it to him and
my actual act of filling is in order to provide him the
water. So whose water is it? Is it my water or is
it his water? Whose תחום tchum does it go by? That's the
debate. Okay. So רב נחמן Rav Nachman says it goes by the
one who was filled for and רב ששת Rav Sheshet says it
goes by the filler.
במאי קמיפלגי? bi'mai kamifligi? What are they debating? מר סבר בירא דהפקרא
הוא ומר סבר בירא דשותפי הוא. mar savar bira de'hefkera hu u'mar
savar bira de'shutfei hu. One says it's a בור bor of הפקר
hefker and the other says it's not really הפקר, hefker, it's really
שותפין. shutfin. Okay. Now, so what does that mean? It means that
if it's הפקר, hefker, רש"י Rashi says we are assuming that if
that the principle is if I pick up, there's a discussion in
בבא מציעא Bava Metzia we're going to end with this as well.
If I see a lost object and I don't need it, I'm
you know, but I know ach here's I don't know a discarded
bicycle. I don't need a bicycle, okay, but I know Charlie's been
dying for a bike so I pick up the bike and I
say I'm going to קונה koneh this for Charlie. מגביה מציאה לחברו.
magbia metzia l'chavero. Does Charlie own the bike now or not? Normally
we say זכין לאדם שלא בפניו, zachin l'adam she'lo be'fanav, right? I
can take possession of something for somebody else not in their presence.
I'm doing him a favor. But here the גמרא Gemara says in
בבא מציעא Bava Metzia but not במקום שחב לאחרים, bi'makom she'chav l'acharin,
not when other people are going to lose out as a result.
So if I pick up the bike for Charlie, this discarded bike,
I'm depriving somebody else of that opportunity, right? So that might be
it might be that מגביה מציאה לחברו לא קנה חברו. magbia metzia
l'chavero lo kanah chavero. I can't do it for him at somebody
else's expense.
That's always true. Yes.
By a case of
מציאה. metzia. Yeah, but not if you're giving me a gift to
be קונה koneh for Charlie. It's always true in a case of
הפקר hefker and מציאה. metzia. Right.
Yeah, so in a case of הפקר hefker that's always the case.
So that's the principle that מגביה מציאה לחברו לא קנה חברו. magbia
metzia l'chavero lo kanah chavero. So רש"י Rashi says we're assuming that
right now, okay? So this water if it's הפקר hefker then if
I draw it for Charlie he's not קונה, koneh, so I'm קונה
koneh and therefore it goes by me. But if it's not an
issue of הפקר, hefker, let's say it's an issue of שותפין, shutfin,
all of כלל ישראל Klal Yisrael is... שותף shutaf in this. So
then when I draw it for Charlie,
right, so then I can be, I mean or certainly Charlie can
be קונה koneh for
himself, but then I can also, so I can be קונה koneh
for Charlie because I'm not taking it away from somebody else. Everybody's
a שותף shutaf and everybody's entitled to take water and to take
their possession and then it sort of becomes a case of ברירה,
breira, right? It's like and we'll see in the גמרא. Gemara. If
partners split some ownership, remember we had the case before about the
barrel of wine that we split or the animal we split on
יום טוב. Yom Tov. Then we would say retroactively you always had
a portion in this well. Retroactively ערב יום טוב Erev Yom Tov
we see that this water was the portion that was always yours
and I maybe can be the agent or whatever you know to
sort of do that divvying up, but I'm not המגביה מציאה לחבירו.
hamagbiah metzia l'chaveiro.
You're not even being מקנה makneh it.
Right, he already owns it. We're just designating which part and retroactively...
Right, retroactively it was always hers, his, okay? So in a normal
case, right, it's not like a city where it's a collective and
it's limited by the city. Here there are multiple different owners, but
the piece that the owner takes retroactively will have been his piece,
his piece from the beginning. So again, by the city it goes
by the collective of the city, here it goes by the individual.
But is it going by the individual because it's הפקר hefker or
is it going by the individual because it's שותפות shutfut and the
part that the שותף shutaf takes then becomes his part retroactively? And
the difference would be I fill it up for Charlie. If it's
הפקר, hefker, then Charlie isn't קונה, koneh, it goes by me. And
if it's שותפות, shutfut, then Charlie is קונה koneh and that would
be the question. ומר סבר בי די שותפותא נינהו? umar savar bei
dei shutfusa ninhu? Okay.
אתיביה רבה לרב נחמן. eisivei Rabbah l'Rav Nachman. Rabbah challenged Rav Nachman,
Rav
Nachman being the one that said it goes by the one for
whom it was filled. It goes by Charlie. הריני hareini which basically
we're saying means what now? Means that it's a concept of שותפות,
shutfut, not a concept of הפקר, hefker, okay? Goes by Charlie. הריני
עליך חרם. hareini alecha cherem. If somebody says, we're back to מודר
הנאה. mudar hana'ah. It says like this: I am on you חרם
cherem which basically means that all of my
objects... I'm sorry, everything that you own is חרם cherem to me.
I am forbidden to get benefit from anything that you own. I'm
able to say that. So המודר אסור. hamudar assur. The one, the
objects... so wait a minute, no,
no, I got it reversed. I'm sorry, I got it reversed. Okay,
so
הריני עליך, hareini alecha, right, I am to you חרם cherem meaning
my things are חרם cherem to you. So all of my objects
are forbidden to you. So המודר, hamudar, the המודר hamudar is the
person I'm the נודר noder and talking to, is forbidden to derive
benefit from anything that I own. Okay. הרי אתה עלי חרם. harei
atah alai cherem. You are for me חרם. cherem. Anything that you
own is forbidden to me. הנודר אסור. hanoder assur. The one making
the vow can't derive benefit from the other person. Okay, basic principle
of vows. You can make your stuff forbidden to others or other
people's things forbidden to you. The only thing you can't do is
make other people's things forbidden to them. Okay, so hold on, I'm
sorry because this is my wife,
so I probably should...
hello? ...okay, fine.
Okay, המודר... hamudar... okay, back to this.
הריני עליך ואתה עלי. hareini alecha v'atah alai. I am forbidden, my
things are forbidden to you and your things are forbidden to me.
So you did both of the things you could do. I can't
get any benefits from you, you can't get any benefits from me.
שניהם אסורים זה בזה. shneihem assurim zeh bazeh. So okay, I can't
get benefit from you and you can't get benefit from me and
it works both directions. But ומותרין, umutarin, here's the things that they
are allowed to derive benefit from. בשל עולי בבל, beshel olei Bavel,
things that are the property of those that come up from בבל,
Bavel, meaning things that are like, as we'll see, הפקר hefker or
communal property. That's going to be the question. ואסורין בשל אותה העיר,
v'assurin beshel osah ha'ir, but they cannot derive benefit from things that
are owned collectively by the city, for things that are owned collectively
by the city they're part of the collective. By the way, this
is the problem of the idea, you know, that the גמרא, Gemara,
developing the גמרא Gemara to deal with the concept of a corporation,
right? Because you know the גמרא Gemara does understand the idea of
belonging to the city and it does contrast that to the idea
of שותפות. shutfut. So you would say that that's a perfect model
for a sense of corporation, like a corporate entity that's not about
the individuals. But here you see that if I can't derive benefit
from you, then I also can't derive benefit from things that are
owned collectively by the city. Well why is that? That's not owned
by you, that's owned by the city as a collective, as a
corporation, presumably not. Presumably things owned by the city are also partly
considered to be owned by you. So the really need to be
like this development, I mean you have the beginning of it, but
this development of this concept of שותפות shutfut to this greater concept
of corporation.
Okay, so that's the difference, is it not, between a private and
a public corporation? In other words, you could use that distinction.
Yeah, maybe, but here still the whole idea of corporation is that
it's not considered to be connected to the individual. Right, and here
it is. Okay, but... a person.
So
I can as well talk to the Supreme Court. So דברים של
אותה העיר. dvarim shel ota ha'ir. And so again, I can't derive
benefit, so if there's a city bathhouse, I can't go to that
city bathhouse cause I'm
a part owner in the bathhouse. And if there's a city synagogue,
I can't go in that synagogue. You're a part owner in that
synagogue. Okay, but I can go to things that are של עולי
בבל. shel olei Bavel. Okay, ואלו הן דברים של עולי בבל. v'elu
hen dvarim shel olei Bavel. Here are the things that are belonging
to עולי בבל. olei Bavel. הר הבית. Har HaBayit. I can go
up to the Temple Mount. Okay? And so it's funny, that doesn't
only belong to עולי בבל, olei Bavel, that belongs to the entire
Jewish people. But that's the point, even to עולי בבל. olei Bavel.
Okay, של הר הבית, shel Har HaBayit, והלשכות, v'halishkot, and the, you
know, chambers in the temple, והעזרות, v'ha'azarot, the עזרה. azara. Okay? ובור
שבאמצע הדרך, ubor she'be'emtza haderech, and the wells that are in, you
know, along the roads. ואלו הן של אותה העיר, v'elu hen shel
ota ha'ir, those are, here are the things that belong to the
city.
הרחוב, harechov, the streets. And I can't walk on the street. As
soon as I say you're forbidden in הנאה hana'ah to me, I
can't walk on the street cause that's partly your street. ובית הכנסת,
uveit haknesset, the synagogue, ובית המרחץ, uveit hamerchatz, and the bathhouse. Okay,
so anyway, if we learn נדרים, Nedarim, that's going to be a
lot of fun to unpack. Really? Anytime I'm מודר mudar somebody הנאה,
hana'ah, all of a sudden I can't use any city institutions? I
can't go to the library, I can't go on the streets, I
can't whatever, get benefit from the streetlamps. Okay, anyway, but the things
belonging to the בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash and the בור של רבים
bor shel rabim are different. Now, presumably, you would say what's the
difference? So presumably, I wouldn't say that that means that those things
are הפקר. hefker. I mean, the בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash isn't הפקר.
hefker. But you could say, well, with the בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash
and the הר הבית Har HaBayit or whatever, those are different because
that's not owned by you guys, that's owned by God. That's הקדש.
hekdesh. Okay, it's owned by the institution called the בית המקדש. Beit
HaMikdash. Right, they had a big treasury, right? They were like, you
know, they were an actual legal institution. Okay, that's part of what
מעילה me'ilah is as well. But how about the well? So again,
is it because the well is considered to be הפקר hefker and
therefore there's no problem? Or again, I think it'd be more interesting
to think that no, that's already just like the corporate entity. Right?
Maybe
a city, עיר, ir, doesn't really mean city, עיר ir means like
village, right, town. Okay, we're not talking about a huge city. But
maybe something that's owned by כל ישראל, Klal Yisrael, maybe that is
more corporate, a concept. But again, the גמרא Gemara is going to
assume that this is evidence that if the well is different than
things of the city, that the why am I not a part
ownership and owner in the well? Must be because it's הפקר. hefker.
Yes.
I just kind of like the idea of the בית המקדש Beit
HaMikdash being הפקר hefker and not acquirable by anybody, like permanently הפקר.
hefker. That's kind of interesting.
Well, הפקר hefker until you draw from the water. Once you draw
from the water, no, because the משנה Mishnah does say it's כרגלי
הממלא. keraglei hamemalay. It doesn't say it's כרגלי כל אדם. keraglei kol
adam. So once you draw from the water, the water is yours.
But the basic ownership of the well is הפקר. hefker. Now again,
you know, what does it mean הפקר? hefker? Could a non-Jew take
from it? You know, if it was dug by Jews and was
dug for עולי בבל. olei Bavel. You know, does it mean, I
mean, you know, does it mean that it's so it's
not acquirable by any individual.
The בור bor is not acquirable. The water is there to be
acquired by whoever. Right. Right.
But the בור bor itself? Right.
I mean, it's a good point. Who controls the, right, that's the
same idea. Who controls the ownership of the בור bor to prevent
somebody from coming and saying, "I've seized the בור, bor, it's הפקר."
hefker. Right. So again, it is a funny way of calling it
הפקר. hefker. It can't be straight הפקר. hefker. It's a very good
point. It has to be, so let's take a look. You know,
maybe you're right. Maybe you'll say, well, no, maybe the ציבור tzibbur
owns the בור, bor, but the ציבור tzibbur is making the water
in the בור bor הפקר. hefker. So okay, so that's anyway, that's
how the גמרא Gemara understands this. So it says
like
this: ואי אמרת בור דשותפי נינהו. vei amart bor d'shutfei ninhu. If
you say the בור, bor, let's say the water of the בור,
bor, the Gozal makes an excellent point. If you say the water
of the בור bor is a partnership, okay, אמאי מותר? amai mutar?
Why is it permissible? How is it any different than any of
the other cases about the בית הכנסת beit haknesset and the street
and so on? דהתנן, dehatnan, and so תוספות Tosafot makes that point,
it obviously wouldn't be different than the other cases that are owned
by the city. But in addition, we teach in a משנה: Mishnah:
השותפין שנדרו הנאה זה מזה. hashutafin shenidru hana'ah ze mizeh. Partners
who were partners in an enterprise, were partners, I don't know, in
a field, in a cow, and we made a vow each of
us can't get הנאה hana'ah one from another. So אסורין ליכנס לחצר.
asurin l'hikans l'chatzer. So if we own a courtyard in partner, a
yard, you can't go into the yard because I'm benefiting from your
portion of it.
ולרחוץ
בבור, velirchotz b'vor, or to, you know,
or to bathe myself in a partnered well because I'm getting benefit
from your portion. So if this is an idea of partnership, why
can I derive benefit from the water of the well? Okay, so
clearly it's an issue of הפקר, hefker, or I would poke maybe
corporate ownership, but anyway, not an issue of partnership. The גמרא Gemara
says: לרחוץ הכא נמי. lirchotz hacha nami. You know what? You're right.
This is a, the well is owned in partnership and it would
be forbidden to jump into a well and to bathe yourself. דהכא
במאי עסקינן. dehacha b'mai askinan. Why does it say that if you
make, if you're forbidden in הנאה, hana'ah, you
can't... To go into the well to immerse yourself, right? People like
saying that like סוכה Sukkah and, you know, טבילה Tevilah are two
מצוות mitzvot that you do with like your entire body. You immerse
yourself, right? So and so you use the whole thing as a
single entity. So it says, look, why can I not go into
the שול shul or the bathhouse or the courtyard that's owned by
the city if there's an איסור הנאה issur hana'ah of one of
the individuals? Because I am using the entire thing. I'm not differentiating
this is my part of the street. I'm walking down the whole
street, I don't have a particular part that's mine. If I were
to jump into the well, I also would be benefiting from his
portion. But if I take water from the well, then I can
say this water isn't his. This is the water that was always
coming to me. יש ברירה. Yesh breira. So before we differentiated it,
it was not known whose water it was. Okay, but once I
take it, then that becomes always my water, that's the idea of
שותפים. shutafim. I'm taking my portion, right? And therefore it's not a
problem. So that's what he says. I can still consist that it's
שותפים, shutafim, but you can take water from the well even though
the איסור הנאה issur hana'ah because of ברירה. breira. Okay, and that's
why, but and when you take water from the well on יום
טוב, Yom Tov, it goes by you because it became yours. Okay,
but if you fill it up for someone else, because of this
concept of שותפים, shutafim, it will belong to the person that you
filled it up for. So that's רב נחמן Rav Nachman saying it
is about שותפות. shutafis.
So the בור bor is owned בשותפים, beshutafim, but the water,
no, the water is owned בשותפות. beshutafus. But once you draw water,
you're taking out your portion. You're allowed to take out of this
part, you know, out of this portion. It's like, you know, it's
like we own the business בשותפות, beshutafus, but we all collect dividends
at the end of the year. You're just collecting some of your
dividends.
And why wouldn't that apply to walking on the street? Every step
I take
in ברירה breira is the piece that I would have owned for
myself.
No, it's not a piece. You're using the whole thing. It's like
jumping into the well to bathe. I'm take this thing as mine.
This thing is what was partly was.
No, this area where my foot is coming down.
What?
It's not exclusively yours. You can't stop somebody else when you're walking
down the street from walking on it if they say, no, I'm
using it now in my time and everybody else off the street.
You can't do that.
I see, so you take water out of the well, if I
grab it from,
it's too late, once you take it, you're entitled as a partner,
סך הכל, sach bakol, to take it and to now take this
as your portion and to exclude other people from it. Okay, so
that can explain why you're allowed in the case of מודר הנאה
mudar hana'ah for ברירה breira and still hold by a concept of
שותפות. shutafus. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says like this.
וסבר רב נחמן יש ברירה? Vesavar Rav Nachman yesh breira? See ברירה
breira something, no, some סוגיות sugyas you can't get away from something.
זבחים, Zevachim, you can't get away from פיגול. pigul. In ביצה, Beitzah,
you can't get away from ברירה. breira. Okay, וסבר רב נחמן יש
ברירה? vesavar Rav Nachman yesh breira? Says רב נחמן Rav Nachman therefore
holds יש ברירה, yesh breira, because he would have to hold that
to explain why the water would not be a problem of הנאה
hana'ah because it always wound up being yours and not joint joint
once it was taken. Does he really hold יש ברירה? yesh breira?
ותנן, Ve'atnan, we taught in the משנה, Mishnah, אחים השותפים, achim hashutafim,
brothers that became partners, which does not mean just סתם stam they
became partners, it means they became partners in the context of their
of the estate they inherited. They inherited an estate, they divided it
up. Okay, while they inherited, by the way, the estate is another
good example that הלכה halakha actually does have of a concept of
a corporation. Before they divide up the estate, it is considered to
be more of a type of a corporate entity. Then they divide
it up, each one gets their portion, and then they decide, you
know what, we'll do better together than apart, they pool it all
again and they make a partnership out of what used to be
the shared estate. Okay, and the הלכה halakha is that once they
divide it up and then reconstitute as a partnership, it has a
status of a partnership. If they had never divided it up, it
would have the status of an estate of a single entity. Now
where does it matter whether this is considered a single entity or
a joint partnered enterprise? So two areas that this משנה Mishnah is
going to pay attention to is שקל, Shekel, remember we learned שקלים,
Shekalim, and מעשר בהמה. ma'aser behemah. I'll start with מעשר בהמה, ma'aser
behemah, which is easier. The הלכה halakha is that if my animals
give birth, as every year all I take all the newborn animals
and I have them walk through a fence, an opening in a
fence, and every tenth one is מעשר בהמה. ma'aser behemah. I am
not obligated to do that if the animals are owned in partnership,
only if they're owned privately, not if they're owned in partnership. Okay,
so if this was an estate that had never been divided, its
animals would not be considered to be owned in partnership. It's a
single entity, the estate, that's the single entity. Okay, and therefore
the brothers would have to take מעשר בהמה. ma'aser behemah. If they
separated and then reconstituted, then it had multiple owners, not a single
entity, it's multiple owners and therefore no מעשר בהמה. ma'aser behemah. The
other case is the case of החצי שקל, hachatzis shekel, right? You
give the החצי שקל hachatzis shekel once a year for the funds
for the בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash. What you're obligated to add to
a החצי שקל, hachatzis shekel, a little coin called a קלבון. kalbon.
which was a moneychanger fee. Now and the Rabbis said is, if
you are basically if partners are giving, no
we're partners, Charlie and me will give a שקל shekel between the
two of us. Nevertheless, bottom line is, we're still two people. We
have to give two פונדיונים. pundions. We're not free. In the end,
we're two people that are just doing it together. But it's not
one entity. However, if the estate is one undivided estate... now interestingly,
it still has to give one שקל shekel for the two brothers.
It doesn't get away with giving just a half שקל, shekel, but
nevertheless, since it's conceived of as one entity, it's only going... in
terms of the פונדיון pundion tax, it's only going to give one
פונדיון. pundion. So that's the משנה. Mishna. So let's take a look.
רב אידי, Rabbi Adu, what's the terminology for corporate? הפקר Hefker or...
No, I don't think it has, you know. תפיסת הבית Tfutsat Habayit
is the phrase that it uses for the this concept of the
estate of the brothers. And that is something comparable. But you'll notice
here with the issue the difference between the city and the public
well, the גמרא Gemara only switches between שותפות Shutafoos and הפקר Hefker
where you could have... that's my point, I don't think it has
a very well-developed sense of corporate... of terminology or sense of corporate
identity, but you do have it to some degree, you do have
it to some... okay, and you do have it to some degree
here by this case of אחים השותפים. Achim Hashutafim. So let's take
a look. Okay, אחים השותפים, Achim Hashutafim, okay, brothers that became partners
in the very estate that they started with. כשחייבים בקולבון פטורים ממעשר
בהמה. Kshechayavim bakalbon pturim mima'aser behema.
When they're obligated in a קולבון, kalbon, which means when they are
considered partners... so because they reconstituted the estate and they're partners, so
they have to give a קולבון kalbon for each person. They're exempt
from מעשר בהמה ma'aser behema because מעשר בהמה ma'aser behema you're exempt
from in this partner state. Okay. וכשחייבים במעשר בהמה פטורים מן הקולבון,
Ukshechayavim bma'aser behema pturim min hakalbon, when they're obligated in מעשר בהמה,
ma'aser behema, which means they never divided the estate, so the estate
exists as one entity, פטורים מן הקולבון, pturim min hakalbon, they're exempt
from the קולבון kalbon because it's one entity. Okay, so that's what
we have, is that if you divide it and reconstitute, you're a
partnership, you're not a corporation. So the גמרא Gemara says like this,
ואמר רב ענן, V'amar Rav Anan, and it says רב ענן, Rav
Anan, לא שנו אלא שחלקו גדיים כנגד טלאים וטלאים כנגד גדיים. Lo
shanu ela shechilku g'dayim k'neged tla'im utla'im k'neged g'dayim.
When is this true that they do not reconstitute the estate? Because
he says there are some times they divided the estate and then
by going back together reconstituted the estate. So that's only when the
division was not a was really a type of a swap, was
not an even division. So if when we initially divided it, I
took the goats and you took the sheep, or you took the
sheep and I took the goats, I don't know if I just
said the same thing, I took the sheep and you took the
goats. Then when we divided it, it was not a natural even
division. Actually, I was buying out your portion in the sheep for
my portion in the goats and vice versa. And therefore we really
did divide, and to come back together it would be a partnership.
That's that scenario. אבל חלקו גדיים כנגד גדיים וטלאים כנגד טלאים, Aval
chilku g'dayim k'neged g'dayim utla'im k'neged tla'im, but
if when we divided it we just took everything down the middle,
okay? You get half the goats, I get half the goats. You
get half the sheep, I get half the sheep. You get half
the house, I get half the house. Okay, everything was straight down
the middle, he says, then there was no purchase going on there.
That was just a natural aspect of inheritance. So for the natural
aspect of inheritance, he says, so... וטלאים כנגד טלאים utla'im k'neged tla'im
אומר זה חלקו המגיע משעה ראשונה לכך. omer ze chelko hamagia mishaa
rishona lakach.
Then ultimately, this is an idea of ברירה. breira. ברירה. Breira. This
is the portion I was always intended to get. Okay, so if
I get half of everything and you get half of everything, this
is your half and that's my half, it's like the case of
partnership, we could say it's not like in the dividing of the
estate you bought something and swapped something with the other person. Okay?
It's basically like this was always what you were going to get.
This was your half and that was the other person's half. And
if that's true, he says, if there was never any purchase and
transaction at the moment of dividing and it was all under the
rubric of inheritance, then the concept of inheritance is still what defines
the
ownership corporate... well, not the way it is now, that it's divided,
because now you have your separate inheritance, but because it was always
under the rubric of inheritance, you can reconstitute the original estate. Okay?
There was never an idea of a business transaction that became part
of it. It was always how do we divvy up the estate.
And since it was all about inheritance and divvying it up, you
can reverse the divvying up and go back to the reality of
estate. That's what he says. רב נחמן אמר, Rav Nachman amar, רב
נחמן Rav Nachman says, אפילו חלקו גדיים כנגד גדיים וטלאים כנגד טלאים
afilu chilku g'dayim k'neged g'dayim utla'im k'neged tla'im אין אומר זה חלקו
המגיע משעה ראשונה לכך. en omer ze chelko hamagia mishaa rishona lakach.
You do not say this was the part you were always going
to get because there's no ברירה, breira, so even if you divided
everything in the middle, there's always an aspect of purchase. I'm getting
these goats, not those goats. Why? Because I'm buying out your portion
in these goats and I'm giving to you for your portion in
those goats. Okay, so there was never an aspect of it... when
it got divided, there was always a sense of buying and selling
and swapping. It was never just a natural issue of always determining
what was mine and therefore it can't be. be reversed. There was
an issue of buying out each other's parts, so now if you
go back together, you can't go back, there's no going back, right?
So therefore, so therefore it would have to be now an aspect
of partnership. What we see from all of that is that רב
נחמן Rav Nachman holds אין ברירה. ein breira. So for רב נחמן
Rav Nachman holds אין ברירה, ein breira, why does now if you
remember the גמרא Gemara said before by the way יש ברירה yesh
breira by דרבנן d'rabbanan and remember that that was also one of
the days I was conveniently absent for?
But we actually פסקן pasken that way. So here there is a
דרבנן d'rabbanan element about the תחומים, tchumim, that's not the problem. The
problem is the נדר neder problem. Because he had to explain this
idea of the well and if it's a well of שותפות, shutafut,
the only way to explain why there's not a נדר neder problem
is by ברירה. breira. And here we hold here that he doesn't
hold of ברירה breira and that's a דאורייתא. d'oraissa.
You have to articulate the שם המפורש shem ha-meforash for a נדר?
neder?
No. Okay so we'll talk about when we do נדרים, Nedarim, but
the answer is no. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says like this:
אלא, Ella, you're right, דכולי עלמא בירא דהפקירא הוא. d'kulei alma bira
d'hefkira hu.
Fine, there's no way of explaining if you hold of אין ברירה
ein breira this case of the well and the נדר neder without
saying that it's הפקר. hefker. Because it's הפקר, hefker, there's no נדר
neder problem. Now, if it's הפקר, hefker, how does רב נחמן Rav
Nachman say that when I fill it up for Charlie, it's it
goes by Charlie? What about מגביה מציאה לחברו לא קנה חברו? magbi'a
metzia l'chavero lo kanah chavero? Why does it go by Charlie? Why
doesn't it go by me? So אלא הכא במגביה מציאה לחברו קמיפלגי.
Ella hacha bi-magbi'a metzia l'chavero ka-mifligi. מר סבר קנה ומר סבר לא
קנה. Mar savar kanah u-mar savar lo kanah.
The question is when I pick it up for somebody else, is
he קונה koneh or not? So what does that mean? So in
the simple sense what it means is you're right, for רב נחמן
Rav Nachman holds that when you draw the water from the well,
Charlie is קונה. koneh. Even though it's a case of מגביה מציאה
לחברו, magbi'a metzia l'chavero, nevertheless he could be קונה. koneh. תוספות Tosafos
explains very simply: maybe in general we would say לא קנה חברו.
lo kanah chavero. But remember what I told you: why is the
reason we say that I can't pick up a lost object for
you? Because somebody else is losing out. So he said: is that
relevant by a well? If it's a well which has a lot
of water and enough water for anybody who needs it, right, even
if you conceptualize it as הפקר, hefker, there would be no problem
of drawing water for someone. רב נחמן Rav Nachman says again: if
I draw it for myself, it becomes mine, then I give it
to Charlie, it's limited by me, that's the משנה. Mishnah. If I
draw it for Charlie, רב נחמן Rav Nachman says now the way
we're concluding, it's הפקר, hefker, I drew it for Charlie, but in
this case Charlie will own it. So Charlie is the first owner
of this water, it goes by him and the רב ששת, Rav
Sheshet, the opposing position says no, Charlie doesn't own it, I own
it, and because I own it, as because I'm the one who
drew it, מגביה מציאה לחברו לא קנה חברו magbi'a metzia l'chavero lo
kanah chavero here and in this case I own it and therefore
it goes by me, not by Charlie. Okay, yes.
Step back to the issue of the flowing waters.
In ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael there were numerous Roman aqueducts that would
have taken water from well beyond the תחום. tchum. But I'm surprised
there's no discussion of that.
That, but was it flowing when יום טוב Yom Tov began? Yeah.
So then that would be the case that it's has no limit.
And maybe that's part of the point of making the point about
flowing waters. But why give that specific scenario, I don't know. Okay
let's just start with the next משנה. Mishnah. מי שהיו פירותיו בעיר
אחרת ועירבו בני אותה העיר
להביא אצלו. Mi she-hayu peirotav b'ir acheret v'irbu b'nei otah ha-ir l'havi
eitzlo. So this was the example I gave you once before, right,
like I'm in Hawaii and I tell you go ahead please use
my house or whatever. Okay so here the scenario is though it's
about me coming in contact with the things that I own. My
fruit are in another city. Here the
scenario is here's City A, okay, this is 2000 אמות, amot, okay,
and here's City B, right, and I don't know this is 2001
or 1000 it doesn't matter. And my fruit is in City B.
Okay so and I just made my עירוב eruv like everybody else
in the city, I didn't make an עירוב תחומים, eruv tchumim, I'm
just with the city. So my fruit starts יום טוב Yom Tov
outside of my תחום. tchum. Okay therefore, but people in B wanted
to come to City A on יום טוב. Yom Tov. So they
made an עירוב eruv here. So they're going to come to City
A, they're entitled okay to come to City A. They cannot bring
the fruit with them. Okay, hey we're coming to you, we'll bring
you the fruit. They can't, because the fruit is חוץ לתחום chutz
la-tchum and therefore you know cannot be brought.
Now the question is, it's your fruit, it's my fruit.
Now the question is okay it can't be brought to me, can
it as this is the question I asked before, can it be
brought anywhere? The fruit sort of starts יום טוב Yom Tov חוץ
לתחום. chutz la-tchum. Right? You got that? It starts יום טוב Yom
Tov חוץ לתחום. chutz la-tchum. It's my fruit, it's already out there
the תחום. tchum. So maybe it can't you know you can't touch
it and move it anywhere. Not just can't bring it all the
way to the city. So we'll talk about that tomorrow.
לא יביאו לו. Lo yavi'u lo. Don't bring the fruit to him.
ואם עירב הוא פירותיו כמוהו. V'im eirev hu peirotav kamohu. But if
I made the עירוב eruv here, then my fruit, if I made
the עירוב, eruv, then my fruit starts in my תחום tchum and
therefore and therefore all is good because then because then it goes
by me. Okay, מי שזימין אצלו אורחים, Mi she-zimin etzlo orchim, so
you invited guests, לא יוליכו בידם מנות. lo yolichu b'yadam manot. So
don't say oh you're going back. Here I invited some guests to
my house from City B. They're now going back to their house
on יום טוב. Yom Tov. Oh here's a little צידה לדרך. tzeidah
la-derech. Again it's יום טוב Yom Tov I can give you a
little fruit to take on the way. You liked that cake so
much, that carrot cake, let me wrap it up for you. Okay,
I can't do that because they're going to be taking my carrot
cake and it's defined by me, so as soon as they get
to here, right to after the 2,000 mark, even though they can
walk back, they can't take my cake back with them.
I don't know, I don't like carrot cake. Okay.
אלא אם כן זכה להם מנותיהם מערב יום טוב, Ela im ken
zachah lahem manoteihem me'erev Yom Tov, unless what I did was on
ערב יום טוב erev Yom Tov I said oh, Rabbi Luria is
coming, he loves my carrot cake and therefore I was קונה koneh
the cake for him before יום טוב, Yom Tov, so I knew
that it would begin יום טוב Yom Tov as his and therefore
I could give it for him that he could take back for
him when he would be going back to his house.
Okay, the גמרא. Gemara.